fortran a compiled imperative programming language famous as the first
fortran 一种已编译的命令式编程语言，以
ever high-level language designed for humans it was developed in the 1950s at
有史以来第一个为人类设计的高级语言而闻名，它是 1950 年代在 ibm 开发的，
ibm by john bakkus a guy who was too lazy to write assembly for the ibm 704
由 johnbakkus 开发
mainframe computer the haters said it would never be as performant as
与
hand-coded programs but by 1957 formula translator became the first computer
手动编码程序一样高效，但到 1957 年，公式翻译器成为第一个计算机
language standard at the time computers were extremely rare but fortran was a
语言标准，当时计算机极为罕见，但 fortran 是一项
huge technical breakthrough because for the first time ever people outside the
巨大的技术突破，因为计算机科学领域以外的人第一次
computer science realm could actually use a computer most importantly the
可以真正使用计算机 最重要的是，该
language implemented the first optimizing compiler which was able to
语言实现了第一个优化编译器，它能够
produce machine code just as fast as anything coded by hand the language has
像任何手工编码一样快速生成
evolved into many different versions over the years and is still in use today
primarily for heavy duty number crunching and scientific computing when
机器码 当
your grandma wrote fortran back in the 70s she didn't have access to fancy
你的祖母在 70 年代写 fortran 时，她无法获得幻想
tools like editors and terminals and instead wrote her code on a punch card
像编辑器和终端这样的工具，而是将她的代码写在一张穿孔卡片上，
each card represents one line of code and is kept neatly in a stack where it
每张卡片代表一行代码，并整齐地保存在堆栈中，
can then be fed into a card reader to be compiled the modern developer can get
然后可以将其输入读卡器进行编译现代开发人员可以
started by installing the fortran compiler then create a file ending in f
通过安装 fortran编译器然后创建一个以 f 或 f95 结尾的文件
or f95 to specify a certain version like fortran 95 use the program keyword to
以指定某个版本，例如fortran 95 使用 program 关键字
give your app a name in older versions keywords used all caps because the shift
为您的应用程序命名在旧版本中关键字使用全部大写，因为
key didn't exist on punch card machines until the 1970s declare variables by
在穿孔卡机器上不存在 shift 键，直到 1970 年代通过
starting with a type followed by a name and optionally a default value any
以类型开头，后跟名称和可选的默认值来声明变量 任何
variable names that start with ijklmn will automatically be considered
以 ijklmn 开头的变量名称都将自动被视为
integers to disable this ancient feature use the implicit nun directive at the
整数以禁用此古老功能在顶部使用隐式 nun 指令
top use the character type to create a string by declaring it with a fixed
使用字符类型创建字符串 通过使用固定的最大长度声明它，
maximum length now print that value to the standard output using the executable
现在使用
statement of print star in addition the dimension keyword can be used to create
print star 的可执行语句以及维度键将该值打印到标准输出 word 可用于创建
an array of numbers and multiple dimensions will create a matrix just be
一个数字数组，多个维度将创建一个矩阵，请
careful not to allocate too much memory because your apple ii only has four
注意不要分配太多内存，因为您的 apple ii 只有 4
kilobytes of ram early versions of the language didn't perform fine-grained
KB ram 早期版本的语言没有执行细粒度的
memory management but modern versions support pointers that can manually
内存管理 但是现代版本支持可以手动
allocate and de-allocate memory but the real killer feature of fortran when it
分配和取消分配内存的指针，但是fortran 在 50 年代问世时真正的杀手级功能是
came out in the 50s is the ability to perform loops perform loose perform
loose the do and do while loops made it relatively easy for anybody to tell a
能够执行循环 告诉
computer how to do something multiple times on top of that fortran also made
计算机如何在该 fortran 之上多次执行某事还使
code reusable with procedures a function procedure takes immutable arguments
代码可与过程重用函数过程接受不可变参数
performs some kind of calculation then returns a value it can be called with
执行某种计算然后返回一个值它可以
its name elsewhere in the code a subroutine is another type of procedure
在代码中的其他地方使用其名称调用子例程是 另
which can take mutable arguments but does not provide a return value now use
一种可以接受可变参数但不提供返回值的过程现在使用
your favorite implementation of the compiler to convert your code into an
您最喜欢的c 实现 编译器将您的代码转换为
executable binary this has been fortran and 100 seconds let me know if you want
可执行的二进制文件，这已经是 fortran和 100 秒，如果您想
to see a full tutorial in the comments thanks for watching and i will see you
在评论中看到完整的教程，请告诉我谢谢观看，我会
in the next one
在下一个